"These are the times,"
"هذه هي الحقبة،
said Thomas Paine,
كما قال طوماس بين،
"that try men's souls."
التي تمتحن أرواح الناس."
And they're trying ours now.
وهي تمتحن أرواحنا الآن.
This is a fateful moment in the history of the West.
هذه لحظة مصيرية في تاريخ الغرب.
We've seen divisive elections and divided societies.
رأينا انتخابات ومجتمعات منقسمة.
We've seen a growth of extremism
رأينا تزايدًا في التطرف
in politics and religion,
في السياسة والدين،
all of it fueled by anxiety, uncertainty and fear,
تذكيها شرارة القلق والشك والخوف،
of a world that's changing almost faster than we can bear,
في عالم يتغير بسرعة أكثر مما نتحمل،
and the sure knowledge that it's going to change faster still.
والعلم اليقين أنه سيستمر في التغير بشكل أكبر.
I have a friend in Washington.
لدي صديق في واشنطن.
I asked him, what was it like being in America
سألته، مالذي يعنيه أن تكون في أمريكا
during the recent presidential election?
خلال الانتخابات الرئاسية الأخيرة؟
He said to me, "Well,
فقال لي: "حسن،
it was like the man
كانت أشبه برجل
sitting on the deck of the Titanic
جالسِ على دفة سفينة التيتانيك
with a glass of whiskey in his hand
وفي يده كأس ويسكي
and he's saying, 'I know I asked for ice --
ويقول: "أعرف أنني طلبت ثلجًا --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but this is ridiculous.'"
لكن هذا تافه."
So is there something we can do,
لذا هل يوجد هناك أمر يمكننا القيام به،
each of us,
كل منا،
to be able to face the future without fear?
لكي نتمكن من مواجهة المستقبل دون خوف؟
I think there is.
أعتقد ذلك.
And one way into it is to see
وإحدى الطرق لرؤية ذلك
that perhaps the most simple way into a culture and into an age
أنه ربما الطريقة الأسهل لفهم ثقافة أو فهم عصر
is to ask: What do people worship?
هو أن تسأل: ما الذي يعبده الناس؟
People have worshipped so many different things --
يعبد الناس مجموعة من الأمور المختلفة --
the sun, the stars, the storm.
الشمس، النجوم، العاصفة.
Some people worship many gods, some one, some none.
قد يعبد بعض الناس عدة آلهة، بعضهم إلهًا واحدًا، وبعضهم لا يعبد أي إله
In the 19th and 20th centuries,
في القرنين 19 والقرن 20،
people worshipped the nation,
كان الناس يعبدون الأمة،
the Aryan race, the communist state.
سباق أريان، الدولة الشيوعية.
What do we worship?
ماذا نعبد نحن؟
I think future anthropologists
أعتقد أن علماء التاريخ في المستقبل
will take a look at the books we read
سينظرون للكتب التي نقرأ
on self-help, self-realization,
عن مساعدة الذات، إدراك الذات،
self-esteem.
التقدير الذاتي.
They'll look at the way we talk about morality
سيرون الطريقة التي نتحدث بها عن الأخلاق
as being true to oneself,
عن أن يكون المرء صادقًا مع نفسه،
the way we talk about politics
الطريقة التي نتحدث بها عن السياسة
as a matter of individual rights,
كحق فردي
and they'll look at this wonderful new religious ritual we have created.
وسينظرون لهذه الطقوس الدينية الرائعة التي أحتدثناها.
You know the one?
هل تعرفونها؟
Called the "selfie."
تلك المسماة " السلفي."
And I think they'll conclude that what we worship in our time
وأعتقد أنهم سيخلصون إلى أن ما نعبده في زماننا
is the self, the me, the I.
هي الذات، الأنا، النفس،
And this is great.
وهذا عظيم.
It's liberating. It's empowering. It's wonderful.
فهذا يشعرك بالتحرر،ب التمكين، وهو رائع.
But don't forget that biologically, we're social animals.
لكن ليس علينا أن ننسى أننا بيولوجيًا حيوانات اجتماعية.
We've spent most of our evolutionary history
فقد قضينا معظم تاريخنا التطوري
in small groups.
في مجموعات صغيرة.
We need those face-to-face interactions
نحتاج للتفاعل وجهًا لوجه
where we learn the choreography of altruism
حيث سنتعلم جمالية الإيثار
and where we create those spiritual goods
ونخلق تلك الأمور الروحية الحميدة
like friendship and trust and loyalty and love
مثل الصداقة والثقة والوفاء والحب
that redeem our solitude.
التي تخلصنا من وحدتنا.
When we have too much of the "I" and too little of the "we,"
حين تكون لدينا الكثير من "الأنا" والقليل جدًا من "نحن،"
we can find ourselves vulnerable,
سنجد أنفسنا ضعفاء،
fearful and alone.
خائفين ووحيدين.
It was no accident that Sherry Turkle of MIT
لم تكن صدفة أن سمت شيري تركل من جامعة إم آي تي
called the book she wrote on the impact of social media
الكتاب الذي ألفته عن تأثير مواقع التواصل الاجتماعي
"Alone Together."
" وحيدون مع بعضنا البعض."
So I think the simplest way of safeguarding the future "you"
لذا فأعتقد أن الطريقة الأسهل لإنقاذ "أنت" المستقبلي
is to strengthen the future "us"
هو أن نقوي "نحن" في المستقبل
in three dimensions:
من خلال ثلاثة أبعاد:
the us of relationship,
"نحن" على مستوى العلاقات
the us of identity
"نحن" على مستوى الهوية،
and the us of responsibility.
و"نحن" على مستوى المسؤولية.
So let me first take the us of relationship.
دعوني أولا أتطرق ل "نحن" على مستوى العلاقات.
And here, forgive me if I get personal.
وهنا سامحوني إن تحدثت عن أمر شخصي.
Once upon a time,
كان يا ما كان،
a very long time ago,
قبل زمن طويل،
I was a 20-year-old undergraduate
كنت طالبًا أبلغ 20 سنة من عمري،
studying philosophy.
أدرس الفلسفة.
I was into Nietzsche and Schopenhauer and Sartre and Camus.
كنت مغرما بكتابات نيتشه وشوبنوهر وسارتر وكامو.
I was full of ontological uncertainty
كنت مفعمًا بالشك
and existential angst.
والأسئلة الوجودية.
It was terrific.
كان ذلك مذهلًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was self-obsessed and thoroughly unpleasant to know,
كنت مهووسًا بذاتي، ولا أشعر بالراحة أن أعرف،
until one day I saw
حتى جاء يوم رأيت فيه
across the courtyard
في فناء الجامعة
a girl
فتاةً
who was everything that I wasn't.
كانت كل شيء لم أكنه.
She radiated sunshine.
كانت تشع نورًا.
She emanated joy.
كانت تشع فرحًا.
I found out her name was Elaine.
عرفت أن اسمها كان إلين.
We met. We talked.
التقينا. تكلمنا.
We married.
تزوجنا.
And 47 years, three children and eight grandchildren later,
وبعد47 سنة، ثلاثة أطفال وثمانية حفدة بعد ذلك،
I can safely say
يمكن أن أقول وأنا متأكد
it was the best decision I ever took in my life,
أن هذا كان أفضل قرار اتخذته في حياتي،
because it's the people not like us
لأن الناس المختلفين عنا
that make us grow.
هم من يجعلوننا نتطور.
And that is why I think
ولهذا فأنا أعتقد
we have to do just that.
أن هذا ماعلينا فعله فحسب.
The trouble with Google filters,
المشكل مع فلترات غوغل،
Facebook friends
وأصدقاء الفايسبوك
and reading the news by narrowcasting rather than broadcasting
وقراءة الأخبار المضيقة للآفاق، عكس تلك الموسعة لآفاق.
means that we're surrounded almost entirely by people like us
يعني أننا محاطون كليا تقريبا بأشخاص يشبهوننا
whose views, whose opinions, whose prejudices, even,
ممن وجهات نظرهم وآراؤهم وحتى أحكامهم
are just like ours.
مماثلة لتلك التي لدينا.
And Cass Sunstein of Harvard has shown
وقد بين كاس سوستاين من هارفارد
that if we surround ourselves with people with the same views as us,
أننا إن أحطنا أنفسنا بأشخاص ممن لديهم نفس وجهات نظرنا،
we get more extreme.
فإننا نصبح أكثر تطرفًا.
I think we need to renew those face-to-face encounters
أعتقد أنه علينا أن نجدد التفاعلات وجهًا لوجه
with the people not like us.
مع من هم ليسوا مثلنا.
I think we need to do that
أعتقد أن علينا أن نقوم بهذا
in order to realize that we can disagree strongly
لكي ندرك أنه يمكننا أن نختلف بقوة
and yet still stay friends.
لكن مع ذلك نظل أصدقاءً
It's in those face-to-face encounters
إذ أنه من خلال التواصل وجهًا لوجه
that we discover that the people not like us
ندرك أن الناس الذين ليسوا مثلنا
are just people, like us.
هم أشخاص، مثلنا فحسب.
And actually, every time
وفي الواقع، في كل مرة
we hold out the hand of friendship
نمد يد الصداقة
to somebody not like us,
لشخص ليس مثلنا،
whose class or creed or color are different from ours,
ممن تكون طبقته أو عقيدته أو لونه مختلفًا عنا،
we heal
فإننا نداوي
one of the fractures
واحدة من الكسور
of our wounded world.
التي يعاني منها كوكبنا المجروح.
That is the us of relationship.
هذه هي "نحن" على مستوى العلاقات.
Second is the us of identity.
ثانيًا هناك نحن على مستوى الهوية.
Let me give you a thought experiment.
دعوني أعطكم تجربة
Have you been to Washington? Have you seen the memorials?
هل سبق أن ذهبتم إلى واشنطن؟ هل رأيتم النصب التذكارية؟
Absolutely fascinating.
إنها مذهلة حقًا.
There's the Lincoln Memorial:
هناك نصب لينكولن:
Gettysburg Address on one side, Second Inaugural on the other.
خطاب جيتيسبورغ من جهة، والافتتاحية الثانية من الجهة الثانية.
You go to the Jefferson Memorial,
تذهب إلى نصب جيفرسون،
screeds of text.
من الكتابة
Martin Luther King Memorial,
نصب مارتن لوثر كينغ،
more than a dozen quotes from his speeches.
عشرات من أقواله المقتبسة من خطاباته.
I didn't realize, in America you read memorials.
لم أكن أدرك أنه في أمريكا تقرؤون النصب التذكارية.
Now go to the equivalent in London in Parliament Square
الآن مايوازي هذا في لندن في ساحة البرلمان
and you will see that the monument to David Lloyd George
وسترى أن نصب ديفيد لويد جورج
contains three words:
يتضمن ثلاث كلمات:
David Lloyd George.
ديفيد لويد جورج.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Nelson Mandela gets two.
حصل نلسون مانديلا على كلمتين.
Churchill gets just one:
شرشيل على كلمة واحدة:
Churchill.
شرشيل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Why the difference? I'll tell you why the difference.
لماذا هذا الفرق؟ سأخبركم سبب الفرق.
Because America was from the outset a nation of wave after wave of immigrants,
لأن أمريكا تشكلت بالأساس من موجة تلو الأخرى من المهاجرين.
so it had to create an identity
فكان عليها أن تخلق هوية
which it did by telling a story
كما فعلت بأن تروي قصة
which you learned at school, you read on memorials
تتعلمها في المدرسة، وتقرؤها في النصب
and you heard repeated in presidential inaugural addresses.
وتسمعها مرارًا في خطابات الافتتاح الرئاسية
Britain until recently wasn't a nation of immigrants,
لم تكن بريطانيا إلى وقت قريب أمة من المهاجرين
so it could take identity for granted.
لذا فقد أخذت موضوع الهوية من المسلمات.
The trouble is now
المشكل هنا
that two things have happened which shouldn't have happened together.
أن أمرين حدثا، لم يكن عليهما أن يحدثا بالتزامن
The first thing is in the West we've stopped telling this story
الأمر الأول أننا في الغرب توقفنا عن رواية هذه القصة
of who we are and why,
عن من نكون، ولماذا،
even in America.
حتى في أمريكا.
And at the same time,
وفي نفس الوقت،
immigration is higher than it's ever been before.
أن الهجرة اليوم أكبر من أي وقت مضى.
So when you tell a story and your identity is strong,
إذًا حينما تروي قصتك وهويتك قوية،
you can welcome the stranger,
يمكنك أن ترحب بالغريب،
but when you stop telling the story,
لكن حين تتوقف عن رواية القصة،
your identity gets weak
تضعف هويتك
and you feel threatened by the stranger.
وتشعر أنك مهدد من طرف الغريب.
And that's bad.
وهذا أمر سيء.
I tell you, Jews have been scattered and dispersed and exiled for 2,000 years.
أقول لكم، كان اليهود مشتتين ومنفين طوال 2000 سنة.
We never lost our identity.
لم نفقد هويتنا قط.
Why? Because at least once a year,
لماذا؟ لأنه مرة في كل سنة،
on the festival of Passover,
في مهرجان باسوفر،
we told our story and we taught it to our children
نروي قصتنا ونعلمها لأطفالنا
and we ate the unleavened bread of affliction
وأكلنا خبز المحنة غير المخمر
and tasted the bitter herbs of slavery.
وتذوقنا أعشاب العبودية المرة.
So we never lost our identity.
لذلك فلم نفقد هويتنا أبدًا.
I think collectively
أعتقد أنه جماعيًا
we've got to get back to telling our story,
علينا أن نعود لنحكي قصتنا،
who we are, where we came from,
من نحن، من أين أتينا،
what ideals by which we live.
ماهي المبادئ التي نعيش عليها.
And if that happens,
وإذا حدث هذا،
we will become strong enough
سنكون أقوياء بما يكفي
to welcome the stranger and say,
لنرحب بالغريب ونقول له،
"Come and share our lives,
" تعال ولنتقاسم حياتنا،
share our stories,
ونتقاسم قصصنا،
share our aspirations and dreams."
ونتقاسم أهدافنا وأحلامنا."
That is the us of identity.
هذه "نحن" على مستوى الهوية.
And finally, the us of responsibility.
وأخيرًا، "نحن" على مستوى المسؤولية.
Do you know something?
هل تعلمون أمرًا؟
My favorite phrase in all of politics,
جملتي المفضلة في السياسة كلها،
very American phrase,
جملة أمريكية للغاية،
is: "We the people."
هي"نحن الناس."
Why "we the people?"
لماذا "نحن الناس؟"
Because it says that we all share collective responsibility
لأنها تقول أننا نتقاسم جميعًا المسؤولية الجماعية
for our collective future.
بخصوص مستقبلنا الجماعي.
And that's how things really are and should be.
وهذا ما يجب أن تسير عليه الأمور فعلًا.
Have you noticed how magical thinking
هل لاحظتم كيف أخذ التفكير السحري
has taken over our politics?
مكانه في سياساتنا؟
So we say, all you've got to do is elect this strong leader
فكل ما نقوله، كل ماعليك فعله هو أن تنتخب هذا الزعيم القوي
and he or she will solve all our problems for us.
وسيقوم هو أو هي بحل كل مشاكلنا.
Believe me, that is magical thinking.
صدقوني هذا هو التفكير السحري.
And then we get the extremes:
بعد ذلك، لدينا التطرفات:
the far right, the far left,
اليمين المتطرف واليسار المتطرف،
the extreme religious and the extreme anti-religious,
المتدين المتطرف واللاديني المتطرف،
the far right dreaming of a golden age that never was,
اليمين المتطرف الذي يحلم بالعصر الذهبي الذي لم يكن قط،
the far left dreaming of a utopia that never will be
واليسار المتطرف الذي يحلم بالمدينة الفاضلة التي لن تحدث قط،
and the religious and anti-religious equally convinced
والمتدينون واللادينيون مقتنعون على حد سواء
that all it takes is God or the absence of God
أن كل مانحتاجه هو الإله أو غياب الإله
to save us from ourselves.
لنخلص أنفسنا من أنفسنا.
That, too, is magical thinking,
هذا أيضا تفكير سحري،
because the only people who will save us from ourselves
لأن الناس الوحيدين الذين سيخلصوننا من أنفسنا
is we the people,
هم نحن الناس،
all of us together.
كلنا جميعًا.
And when we do that,
وحين نقوم بهذا،
and when we move from the politics of me
وحينما نتجاوز سياسات الأنا
to the politics of all of us together,
إلى سياساتنا جميعًا،
we rediscover those beautiful, counterintuitive truths:
سنكتشف تلك القصص الجميلة غير العادية:
that a nation is strong
أن الأمة قوية
when it cares for the weak,
حين تهتم بالضعيف،
that it becomes rich
أنها تصبح غنية
when it cares for the poor,
حين تهتم بالفقير،
it becomes invulnerable when it cares about the vulnerable.
ستكون غير هشة حين تهتم بالطبقات الهشة
That is what makes great nations.
هذا ما يصنع أممًا عظيمة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So here is my simple suggestion.
لذا إليكم اقتراحي البسيط
It might just change your life,
قد يغير حياتكم،
and it might just help to begin to change the world.
وقد يساعد في بداية تغيير العالم.
Do a search and replace operation
قم ببحث واستبدل طريقة
on the text of your mind,
في النص في ذهنك،
and wherever you encounter the word "self,"
وكلما صادفت كلمة "ذات"،
substitute the word "other."
استبدلها بكلمة "الآخر."
So instead of self-help, other-help;
فعوضًا عن "مساعدة الذات"، مساعدة الآخر،
instead of self-esteem, other-esteem.
عوَضًا عن تقدير الذات، تقدير الآخر.
And if you do that,
وحين تقوم بذلك،
you will begin to feel the power
ستبدأ في الشعور بقوة
of what for me is one of the most moving sentences
بما يشكل بالنسبة لي إحدى أكثر الجمل إلهامًا
in all of religious literature.
في كل الأدب الديني.
"Though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death,
"رغم أنني أسير خلال وادي ظل الموت،
I will fear no evil,
لن أخاف الشر،
for you are with me."
لأنك معي."
We can face any future without fear
يمكننا أن نواجه أي مستقبل دون خوف
so long as we know
طالما أننا نعرف
we will not face it alone.
أننا لن نواجهه بمفردنا.
So for the sake of the future "you,"
لذا، من أجل "أنت المستقبلي،"
together let us strengthen
جميعًا، فلنقوٍّ
the future "us."
"نحن" في المستقبل.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)